<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">

<appendix id="gtadmin-packaging" xreflabel="Packaging Details for Installing GT"><title>Packaging details</title>
<section id="gtadmin-makefile"><title>The makefile</title>
<para>
You do not have to build every subcomponent of this release.  The
makefile specifies subtargets for different functional subpieces.
</para>

<itemizedlist><title>Makefile targets</title>

<listitem><simpara>gram: GRAM5
</simpara></listitem>
<listitem><simpara>gridftp: GridFTP
</simpara></listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
Note that all of these targets require the "install" target also.
So, for instance, to build GridFTP alone, you would run:

<screen>
$ ./configure --prefix=/path/to/install
$ make gridftp install
</screen>
</para>
</section>
<section>
    <title>Linking with Globus Toolkit Libraries</title>
    <para>
        
        Since GT 2.0, the toolkit has included a script called globus-makefile-header that can be used to assemble the 
        cflags and link line information when linking a program with libraries included in the toolkit.  This script 
        would walk the package metadata dependency tree to ensure that all needed flags were included, without duplicates.
        This method worked, and continues to work in GT <replaceable role="entity">version</replaceable>, but we consider it to be obsolete, as we have added support 
        for using <ulink url=" http://www.freedesktop.org/wiki/Software/pkg-config">pkg-config</ulink>
    </para>
    <para>
        
        Pkg-config is very similar in concept to globus-makefile-header, but it has gained widespread adoption across a range of unix platforms.
    </para>
    <para>
        To get the cflags and link line information to link to the globus-ftp-client library, for example, you could
        <screen><prompt>$</prompt><userinput>pkg-config --cflags --libs globus-ftp-client</userinput></screen>
    </para>
    <para>
        Each Globus Toolkit library has a pkg-config metadata file that is installed as part of its devel package. 
    </para>
    <para>
        For more information about pkg-config, please see <ulink url="http://www.freedesktop.org/wiki/Software/pkg-config">the pkg-config homepage.</ulink>
    </para>
</section>
</appendix>
