<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"
[

<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../xinclude.mod" >
%xinclude;

]>
<book id="gridftpKey">
  <title>GT <replaceable role="entity">version</replaceable> GridFTP Key Concepts</title>
  <titleabbrev>GridFTP Key Concepts</titleabbrev> 

  <bookinfo id="gridftp-key-overview"><abstract><title>Overview</title>
<para>One of the foundational issues in HPC computing is the ability to move
large (multi Gigabyte, and even Terabyte), file-based data sets between sites.
Simple file transfer mechanisms such as FTP and SCP are not sufficient either
from a reliability or performance perspective. GridFTP extends the standard FTP
protocol to provide a high-performance, secure, reliable protocol for bulk data
transfer.</para></abstract>
</bookinfo>

  <chapter id="gridftp-key-advantages"><title>GridFTP Protocol</title>
<!-- 
  If you are not familiar with FTP in general, it might be a good idea to browse
  relevant definitions [fixme here - olink to glossary].
  -->

<para>
GridFTP is a protocol defined by Global Grid Forum Recommendation GFD.020,
  RFC 959, RFC 2228, RFC 2389, and a draft before the IETF FTP working group. Key
  features include:
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem><simpara>Performance - GridFTP protocol supports using parallel TCP
  streams and multi-node transfers to achieve high
  performance.</simpara></listitem>
  <listitem><simpara>
  Checkpointing - GridFTP protocol requires that the server send restart markers
  (checkpoint) to the client.
  </simpara></listitem>
  <listitem><simpara>
  Third-party transfers - The FTP protocol on which GridFTP is based separates control and data channels, enabling third-party transfers, that is, the transfer of data between two end hosts, mediated by a third host.
  </simpara></listitem>
  <listitem><simpara>
  Security - Provides strong security on both control and data channels. Control
  channel is encrypted by default. Data channel is authenticated by default with
  optional integrity protection and encryption. 
  </simpara></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
  </para>
</chapter>

  <chapter id="globus-gridftp"><title>Globus Implementation of GridFTP</title>
  <para>
  The GridFTP protocol provides for the secure, robust, fast and efficient transfer
  of (especially bulk) data. The Globus Toolkit provides the most commonly used
  implementation of that protocol, though others do exist (primarily tied to
  proprietary internal systems). </para>
<para>The Globus Toolkit provides:</para>
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem><simpara>a server implementation
          called <computeroutput>globus-gridftp-server</computeroutput>,</simpara></listitem>
  <listitem><simpara> a scriptable command line client called <computeroutput>globus-url-copy</computeroutput>, and</simpara></listitem>
  <listitem><simpara>a set of development libraries for custom clients. </simpara></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>While the Globus
  Toolkit does not provide a client with Graphical User Interface (GUI), <ulink
  url="http://www.globusonline.org">Globus Online</ulink> provides a web GUI for
  GridFTP data movement. </para>
<para>
Globus GridFTP framework implements all the key features of GridFTP protocol
mentioned above. It supports both Grid Security Infrastructure (GSI) and SSH for
securing the data transfer. Unlike sftp, SSH based GridFTP supports multiple
security options on the data channel - authentication only, authentication and
integrity protection, fully encrypted. Globus implemention of GridFTP is modular
and extensibl. XIO based Globus GridFTP framework makes it easy to plugin
alternate transport protocols. The Data Storage Interface (DSI) allows for
easier integration with various storage systems. We currently have DSIs for
POSIX filesystems (default) and HPSS. Globus GridFTP has been deployed at
thousands of sites with more than 10 million data transfers per day.</para>
</chapter>

<chapter id="gridftp-clients"><title>GridFTP Clients</title>
<para> <ulink url="http://www.globusonline.org">Globus Online</ulink> is the recommended interface to move data to and from
GridFTP servers. Globus Online provides a web GUI, command line interface and a
REST API for GridFTP data movement. It provides automatic fault recovery and
automatic tuning of optimization parameters to achieve high performance. </para>  
<para>
The Globus Toolkit provides a GridFTP client called
<computeroutput>globus-url-copy</computeroutput>, a command line interface, suitable for scripting. For example,
the following command:</para>
<screen>globus-url-copy gsiftp://remote.host.edu/path/to/file file:///path/on/local/host</screen>
<para>would transfer a file from a remote host to the locally accessible path specified
in the second URL.</para>
<para>Finally, if you wish to add access to files stored behind GridFTP servers,
  or you need custom client functionality, you can use our very powerful client
library to develop custom client functionality.</para>
<para>
  For more information about GridFTP, see:</para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><simpara>the <olink targetdoc="gridftp">documentation</olink>.</simpara></listitem>
    <listitem><simpara><ulink url="http://www.globus.org/alliance/publications/papers/gridftp_final.pdf">The Globus Striped GridFTP Framework and Server</ulink></simpara></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  
</chapter>


  <glossary role="auto" id="glossary-gridftpKey">
    <remark><glossterm>GridFTP</glossterm></remark>
    <glossdiv><title>A</title>
      <glossentry>
        <glossterm>Dummy term</glossterm>
        <glossdef>
          <para>This is a dummy entry for the automatic glossary database. Do not edit.</para>
        </glossdef>
      </glossentry>
    </glossdiv>
  </glossary>
</book>
