<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"
[

<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../xinclude.mod" >
%xinclude;

]>
<book id="gram5Key">
  <title>GT <replaceable role="entity">version</replaceable> GRAM5 Key Concepts</title>
  <titleabbrev>GRAM5 Key Concepts</titleabbrev>
  <bookinfo id="gram5-key-overview">
    <abstract>
      <title>Overview</title>
      <para> The Globus Toolkit provides GRAM5: a service to submit, monitor, and cancel jobs on
        Grid computing resources. In GRAM, a job consists of a computation and, optionally, file
        transfer and management operations related to the computation. Some users, particularly
        interactive ones, benefit from accessing output data files as the job is running. Monitoring
        consists of querying and/or subscribing for status information, such as job state changes. </para>
      <para> Grid computing resources are typically managed by a local resource manager which
        implements allocation and prioritization policies while optimizing the execution of all
        submitted jobs for efficiency and performance according to site policy. GRAM is not a
        resource scheduler, but rather a protocol engine for communicating with a range of different
        local resource schedulers using a standard message format. </para>
    </abstract>
  </bookinfo>
  <chapter id="gram5-key-concepts">
    <title>Conceptual details</title>
    <para> A number of concepts underly the purpose and motivation for GRAM. These concepts are
      divided into broad categories below. </para>
    <section>
      <title>Targeted job types</title>
      <para> GRAM is meant to address a range of jobs where arbitrary programs, reliable operation,
        stateful monitoring, credential management, and file staging are important. GRAM is not
        meant to serve as a "remote procedure call" (RPC) interface for applications not requiring
        many of these features. Furthermore, its interface model and implementation may be too
        costly for such uses. The GRAM5 service protocols and implementation will always involve
        multiple round-trips to support these advanced features that are not required for simple RPC
        applications. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Component architecture</title>
      <para> Rather than consisting of a monolithic solution, GRAM is based on a component
        architecture at both the protocol and software implementation levels. This component
        approach serves as an ideal which shapes the implementation as well as the abstract design
        and features. </para>
      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Service model</entry>
              <entry>
                <para> For GRAM5, the <command>globus-gatekeeper</command> daemon and GSI library
                  are used for secure communications and service dispatch. </para>
                <para> The <command>globus-job-manager</command> daemon implements the job
                  management and file transfer functionality. </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry><glossterm baseform="LRM Adapter">Local Resource Manager Adapters</glossterm></entry>
              <entry>
                <para> GRAM provides a scripted plug-in architecture to enable extension with
                  adapters to control a variety of local resource systems. </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Security</title>
      <informaltable>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>Secure operation</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>GRAM5 uses SSL-based protocols to establish identity or provide other security
                  tokens needed to authorize GRAM5 service requests. Once authorized, each instance
                  of the job service runs as a local POSIX user. GRAM5 restricts job monitoring and
                  management operations to those who are authorized by the local site policy.
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Local system protection domains</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>To protect users from each other, the GRAM5 job manager and the jobs it starts
                  are executed in separate local security contexts. Additionally, GRAM mechanisms
                  used to interact with the local resource are designed to minimize the privileges
                  required and to minimize the risks of service malfunction or compromise. </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Credential delegation and management</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>A client delegates some of its rights to the GRAM service in order to allow it
                  to perform file transfers on behalf of the client and send state notifications to
                  registered clients. Additionally, GRAM5 provides per-job credentials so that job
                  instances may perform further authentication with other services. </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Audit</entry>
              <entry>
                <para>GRAM uses a range of audit and logging techniques to record a history of job
                  submissions and critical system operations. These records may be used to assist
                  with accounting functions as well as to further mitigate risks from abuse or
                  malfunction.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="GRAM5_Approach.xml"/>
  <glossary role="auto" id="gram5Key-glossary">
            <remark>
                <!--some terms not in the docs but wanted in glossary: -->
            <glossterm>Grid Resource Allocation and Management</glossterm>
            <glossterm>Local Resource Manager</glossterm>
            </remark>
            <glossdiv><title>A</title>
                <glossentry>
                    <glossterm>Dummy term</glossterm>
                    <glossdef>
                        <para>This is a dummy entry for the automatic glossary database. Do not edit.</para>
                    </glossdef>
                </glossentry>
            </glossdiv>
  </glossary>
</book>
