<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"
[
    <!ENTITY elephant "<systemitem class='systemname'>elephant</systemitem>" >
    <!ENTITY donkey "<systemitem class='systemname'>donkey</systemitem>" >

    <!ENTITY rootuser "<systemitem class='username'>root</systemitem>" >
    <!ENTITY myproxyuser "<systemitem class='username'>myproxy</systemitem>" >
    <!ENTITY quser "<systemitem class='username'>quser</systemitem>" >

    <!ENTITY doquserprompt "<prompt>quser@donkey&#37; </prompt>" >
    <!ENTITY passphrase "<userinput>******</userinput>" >
]
>
    <section id="q-prereq">
        <title>Prerequisites</title>
        <para>
            We distribute the Globus Toolkit <replaceable
            role="entity">shortversion</replaceable> as a set of RPM and Debian
            packages for Linux systems, as an installable package for Mac OS X,
            as a .zip file for Windows and Cygwin, as well as a source
            installer which can be used on other operating systems. In this
            quickstart, we will be
            installing RPM packages. Thus, it is a prerequisite for following
            this quickstart that you are running a distribution for which we
            provide RPMs. If you are running a supported Debian or Ubuntu
            system, the process is very similar, but you'll need to use the
            <command>apt-get</command> or similar tools to install the
            packages. For the source installer, there is more work involved,
            and you'll need to consult the full installation guide.
        </para>
        <para>
            First, we will to set up our system to use the Globus package
            repository. This repository contains the Globus software packages,
            signed by our build manager. We provide RPM and Debian packages
            that contain a source configuration file and the public key which
            can be used to verify the packages.  If your distribution has
            Globus <replaceable role="entity">version</replaceable> packages
            within its repository, you can skip to the next section.
        </para>
        <para>
            The globus toolkit package repo RPM can be downloaded from
            <ulink
            url="http://www.globus.org/ftppub/gt6/installers/repo/globus-toolkit-repo-latest.noarch.rpm">the repo RPM package on globus.org</ulink>.
        </para>
        <para>
            To install binary RPMs, download the globus-toolkit-repo
            package from the link above and install it with the command:
            <screen><prompt role="root"/><command>rpm -hUv globus-toolkit-repo-latest.noarch.rpm</command></screen>
        </para>
        <para>
        The globus toolkit package repo Debian file can be downloaded from
            <ulink
            url="http://www.globus.org/ftppub/gt6/installers/repo/globus-toolkit-repo_latest_all.deb">the repo Debian package on globus.org</ulink>.
        </para>
        <para>
            To install Debian or Ubuntu package, download the
            globus-toolkit-repo package from the link above and install it with
            the command:
            <screen><prompt role="root"/><command>dpkg -i globus-toolkit-repo_latest_all.deb</command></screen>
        </para>
        <para>
            Once you've installed the Globus repository package, you can use
            your operating system's packaging tools: 
            <command>yum</command> or <command>apt-get</command>, to install
            the Globus components.
        </para>
        <important>
            <para>
                For operating systems based on RHEL (such as Red Hat Enterprise
                Linux, CentOS, and Scientific Linux), the compatible EPEL
                repository must be enabled before installing myproxy. For OS
                versions 5.x, install the <ulink
                url="http://download.fedoraproject.org/pub/epel/5/i386/epel-release-5-4.noarch.rpm">EPEL
                5 package</ulink>, and for OS version 6.x, use <ulink
                url="http://download.fedoraproject.org/pub/epel/6/i386/epel-release-6-7.noarch.rpm">
                6 package</ulink>.
            </para>
            <para>
                For information about installing these, see the <ulink
                url="http://fedoraproject.org/wiki/EPEL/FAQ#How_can_I_install_the_packages_from_the_EPEL_software_repository.3F">EPEL
                FAQ</ulink>.
            </para>
            <para>
                This step is not needed for Fedora, Debian, or Ubuntu systems.
            </para>
        </important>
        <important>
            <para>
                For SUSE Linux Enterprise Server systems which will be using
                globus-connect-server, a newer version of apache2 must be
                installed in order for myproxy-oauth to work. This is available
                by adding the Apache2 and Apache2 Modules for SLES11
                repositories from opensuse.org.
            </para>
            <para>
                These can be installed by running these commands:
                <screen><prompt role="root"/><command>zypper ar http://download.opensuse.org/repositories/Apache/SLE_11_SP3/Apache.repo</command>
<prompt role="root"/><command>zypper ar http://download.opensuse.org/repositories/Apache:/Modules/Apache_SLE_11_SP3/Apache:Modules.repo</command>
<prompt role="root"/><command>rpm --import http://download.opensuse.org/repositories/Apache/SLE_11_SP3/repodata/repomd.xml.key</command>
<prompt role="root"/><command>rpm --import http://download.opensuse.org/repositories/Apache:/Modules/Apache_SLE_11_SP3/repodata/repomd.xml.key</command></screen>
            </para>
        </important>
    </section>
