<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" [

<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY prompt "<prompt>&#37; </prompt>" >
<!ENTITY GRAM "GRAM5" >
]>
<section id="gram5-troubleshooting-admin">
    <title>Admin Troubleshooting</title>
    <section>
        <title>Security</title>
        <para>GRAM requires a host certificate and private key in order for the <command
                >globus-gatekeeeper</command> service to run. These are typically located in
                <filename>/etc/grid-security/hostcert.pem</filename> and <filename
                >/etc/grid-security/hostkey.pem</filename>, but the path is configurable in the
                <olink targetdoc="gram5Admin" targetptr="gram5-configuring-gatekeeper">gatekeeper
                configuration file</olink>. The key must be protected by file permissions allowing
            only the root user to read it. </para>
        <para>GRAM also (by default) uses a <filename>grid-mapfile</filename> to authorize Grid
            users as local users. This file is typically located in <filename
                >/etc/grid-security/grid-mapfile</filename>, but is configurable in the <olink
                targetdoc="gram5Admin" targetptr="gram5-configuring-gatekeeper">gatekeeper
                configuration file</olink>. </para>
        <para>Problems in either of these configurations will show up in the gatekeeper log
            described below. See the <olink targetdoc="gsic">GSI</olink> documentation for more
            detailed information about obtaining and installing host certificates and maintaining a
                <filename>grid-mapfile</filename>. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Verify that Services are Running</title>
        <para>GRAM relies on the <command>globus-gatekeeper</command> program and (in some cases)
            the <command>globus-scheduler-event-generator</command> programs to process jobs. If the
            former is not running, jobs requests will fail with a "connection refused" error. If the
            latter is not running, GRAM jobs will appear to "hang" in the <literal>PENDING</literal>
            state. </para>
        <para>The <command>globus-gatekeeper</command> is typically started via an init script
            installed in <filename>/etc/init.d/globus-gatekeeper</filename>. The command <command
                >/etc/init.d/globus-gatekeeper status</command> will indicate whether the service is
            running. See <olink targetdoc="gram5Admin" targetptr="gram5-admin-starting-and-stopping"
            /> for more information about starting and stopping the <command
                >globus-gatekeeper</command> program. </para>
        <para>If the <command>globus-gatekeeper</command> service fails to start, the output of the
            command <command>globus-gatekeeper -test</command> will output information describing
            some types of configuration problems. </para>
        <para>The <command>globus-scheduler-event-generator</command> is typically started via an
            init script installed in <filename
                >/etc/init.d/globus-scheduler-event-generator</filename>. It is only needed when the
            LRM-specific "setup-seg" package is installed. The command <command
                >/etc/init.d/globus-scheduler-event-generator status</command> will indicate whether
            the service is running. See <olink targetdoc="gram5Admin"
                targetptr="gram5-admin-starting-and-stopping"/> for more information about starting
            and stopping the <command>globus-scheduler-event-generator</command> program. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Verify that LRM packages are installed</title>
        <para> The <command>globus-gatekeeper</command> program starts the <command
                >globus-job-manager</command> service with different command-line parameters
            depending on the LRM being used. Use the command <command>globus-gatekeeper-admin
                -l</command> to list which LRMs the gatekeeper is configured to use. </para>
        <para> The <command>globus-job-manager-script.pl</command> is the interface between the GRAM
            job manager process and the LRM adapter. The command <command
                >/usr/share/globus/globus-job-manager-script.pl -h</command> will print the list of
            available adapters.
            <screen>&prompt;<command>/usr/share/globus/globus-job-manager-script.pl -h</command>
<computeroutput>USAGE: /usr/share/globus/globus-job-manager-script.pl -m MANAGER -f FILE -c COMMAND
Installed managers: condor fork</computeroutput></screen></para>
        <para> The <command>globus-scheduler-event-generator</command> also uses an LRM-specific
            module to generate scheduler events for GRAM to reduce the amount of resources GRAM uses
            on the machine where it runs. To determine which LRMs are installed and configured, use
            the command <command>globus-scheduler-event-generator-admin -l</command>.
            <screen>&prompt;<command>globus-scheduler-event-generator-admin -l</command>
<computeroutput>fork [DISABLED]</computeroutput></screen></para>
        <para> If any of these do not show the LRM you are trying to use, install the relevant
            packages related to that LRM and restart the GRAM services. See the <olink
                targetdoc="gram5Admin">GRAM Administrator's Guide</olink> for more information about
            starting and stopping the GRAM services. </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Verify that the LRM packages are configured</title>
        <para> All &GRAM; LRM adapters have a configuration file for site customizations, such as
            queue names, paths to executables needed to interface with the LRM, etc. Check that the
            values in these files are correct. These files are described in <olink
                targetdoc="gram5Admin" targetptr="gram5-configuring-lrm"/>. </para>
    </section>
    <section id="gram5-troubleshooting-gatekeeper-log">
        <title>Check the Gatekeeper Log</title>
        <para> The <filename>/var/log/globus-gatekeeper.log</filename> file contains information
            about service requests from clients, and will be useful when diagnosing service startup
            failures, authentication failures, and authorization failures. </para>
        <section>
            <title>Authorization failures</title>
            <para> GRAM uses GSI to authenticate client job requests. If there is a problem with the
                GSI configuration for your host, or a client is trying to connect with a certificate
                signed by a CA your host does not trust, the job request will fail. This will show
                up in the log as a "GSS authentication failure". See the <olink
                    targetdoc="gsicAdmin">GSI Administrator's Guide</olink> for information about
                diagnosing authentication failures. </para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Gridmap failures</title>
            <para> After authentication is complete, GRAM maps the Grid identity to a local user
                prior to starting the <command>globus-job-manager</command> process. If this fails,
                an error will show up in the log as "globus_gss_assist_gridmap() failed
                authorization". See the <olink targetdoc="gsicAdmin">GSI Administrator's
                    Guide</olink> for information about managing gridmap files. </para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section id="gram5-troubleshooting-jobmanager-log">
        <title>Job Manager Logs</title>
        <para> A per-user job manager log is typically located in
            <filename>/var/log/globus/gram_<replaceable>$USERNAME</replaceable>.log</filename>.
            This log contains information from the job manager as it attempts
            to execute GRAM jobs via a local resource manager. The logs can be
            fairly verbose. Sometimes looking for log entries near those
            containing the string <literal>level=ERROR</literal> will show more information
            about what caused a particular failure.
        </para>

        <para>
            Once you've found an error in the log, it is generally useful to find log entries
            related to the job which hit that error. There are two job IDs associated with
            each job, one a GRAM-specific ID, and one an LRM-specific ID. To determine the
            GRAM ID associated with a job, look for the attribute
            <literal>gramid</literal> in the log message. Finding that, looking for all
            other log messages which contain that <literal>gramid</literal> value will
            give a better picture of what the job manager is doing. To determine the
            LRM-specific ID, look for a message at <literal>TRACE</literal> level with the
            matching GRAM ID found above with the <literal>response</literal> value matching
            <literal>GRAM_SCRIPT_JOB_ID:</literal><replaceable>LRM-ID</replaceable>. You
            can then find follow the state of the <replaceable>LRM-ID</replaceable> as well
            as the GRAM ID in the log, and correlate the <replaceable>LRM-ID</replaceable>
            information with local resource manager logs and administrative tools.
        </para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Email Support</title>
        <para> If all else fails, please send information about your problem to
                <email>gram-user@globus.org</email>. You'll have to subscribe to a list before you
            can send an e-mail to it. See <ulink url="http://dev.globus.org/wiki/Mailing_Lists"
                >here</ulink> for general e-mail lists and information on how to subscribe to a list
            and <ulink url="http://dev.globus.org/wiki/GRAM#Mailing_Lists">here</ulink> for
            GRAM-specific lists. Depending on the problem, you may be requested to file a bug report
            to the Globus project's <ulink url="https://globus.atlassian.net">Issue Tracker</ulink>.
        </para>
    </section>
</section>
