<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="gram5-audit-logging"><title>Audit Logging</title>
  <indexterm type="gram5"><primary>audit logging</primary></indexterm>
  <section id="gram5-audit-logging-overview">
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>GRAM5 includes mechanisms to provide access to audit and accounting information associated
      with jobs that GRAM5 submits to a local resource manager (LRM) such as Torque, GridEngine, or
      Condor.</para>
    <para>In some scenarios, it is desirable to get general information about the usage of the
      underlying LRM, such as:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>What kinds of jobs were submitted via GRAM?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>How long did the processing of a job take?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>How many jobs were submitted by user X?</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para> The following three use cases give a better overview of the meaning and purpose of
      auditing and accounting:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Group Access</emphasis>: A grid resource provider allows a remote
          service (e.g., a gateway or portal) to submit jobs on behalf of multiple users. The grid
          resource provider only obtains information about the identity of the remote submitting
          service and thus does not know the identity of the users for which the grid jobs are
          submitted. This group access is allowed under the condition that the remote service stores
          audit information so that, if and when needed, the grid resource provider can request and
          obtain information to track a specific job back to an individual user. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Query Job Accounting</emphasis>: A client that submits a job needs
          to be able to obtain, after the job has completed, information about the resources
          consumed by that job. In portal and gateway environments where many users submit many jobs
          against a single allocation, this per-job accounting information is needed soon after the
          job completes so that client-side accounting can be updated. Accounting information is
          sensitive and thus should only be released to authorized parties. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Auditing</emphasis>: In a distributed, multi-site environment, it
          can be necessary to investigate various forms of suspected intrusion and abuse. In such
          cases, we may need to access an audit trail of the actions performed by a service. When
          accessing this audit trail, it will frequently be important to be able to relate specific
          actions to the user. </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>Audit logging in GRAM5 is done when a job completes.</para>
  </section><section>
    <title>Audit and Accounting Records</title>
    <para>While audit and accounting records may be generated and stored by different entities in
      different contexts, we make the following assumptions in this chapter:</para>
    <informaltable>
      <tgroup cols="3">
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>
            </entry>
            <entry>Audit Records</entry>
            <entry>Accounting Records</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>Generated by:</entry>
            <entry>GRAM service</entry>
            <entry>LRM to which the GRAM service submits jobs</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Stored in:</entry>
            <entry>Database, indexed by GJID</entry>
            <entry>LRM, indexed by JID</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>Data that is stored:</entry>
            <entry>See list below.</entry>
            <entry>May include all information about the duration and resource-usage of a
              job</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
    <para> The audit record of each job contains the following data:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">job_grid_id</emphasis>: String representation of the resource EPR
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">local_job_id</emphasis>: Job/process id generated by the scheduler
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">subject_name</emphasis>: Distinguished name (DN) of the user
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">username</emphasis>: Local username </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">idempotence_id</emphasis>: Job id generated on the client-side
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">creation_time</emphasis>: Date when the job resource is created
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">queued_time</emphasis>: Date when the job is submitted to the
          scheduler </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">stage_in_grid_id</emphasis>: String representation of the
          stageIn-EPR (RFT) </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">stage_out_grid_id</emphasis>: String representation of the
          stageOut-EPR (RFT) </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">clean_up_grid_id</emphasis>: String representation of the
          cleanUp-EPR (RFT) </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">globus_toolkit_version</emphasis>: Version of the server-side GT
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">resource_manager_type</emphasis>: Type of the resource manager
          (Fork, Condor, ...) </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">job_description</emphasis>: Complete job description document
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">success_flag</emphasis>: Flag that shows whether the job failed or
          finished successfully </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">finished_flag</emphasis>: Flag that shows whether the job is
          already fully processed or still in progress </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="strong">gateway_user</emphasis>: Teragrid identity of the user which
          submitted the job. </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section><section>
    <title>For More Information</title>
    <para>The rest of this chapter focuses on how to configure GRAM5 to enable Audit-Logging.
    </para>
  </section><section id="gram5-audit-logging-config">
    <title>Configuration</title>
    <para>Audit logging is turned off by default. To enable GRAM5 audit logging, in the job manager,
      add the command-line option <option>-audit-directory
          <replaceable>AUDIT-DIRECTORY}</replaceable></option> to the job manager configuration in
      one of the following locations: <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <simpara><filename><envar>$GLOBUS_LOCATION</envar>/etc/globus-job-manager.conf</filename>
            to enable it for all job manager services</simpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <simpara><filename><envar>$GLOBUS_LOCATION</envar>/etc/grid-services/<replaceable>LRM_SERVICE_NAME</replaceable></filename>
            to enable it for a particular job manager service for a particular LRM.</simpara>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>
  </section><section id="gram5-audit-logging-config-database">
    <title>Audit Database Interface</title>
    <para>The <command>globus-gram-audit</command> program reads GRAM5 audit records and loads those
      records into a SQL database. This program is available as part of the <application
        >globus_gram_job_manager_auditing</application> package. It must be configured by installing
      and running the <application>globus_gram_job_manager_auditing_setup_scripts</application>
      setup package via <command>gpt-postinstall</command>. This setup script creates the <filename
          ><envar>$GLOBUS_LOCATION</envar>/etc/globus-job-manager-audit.conf</filename>
      configuration file described below and creates database tables needed by the audit system. </para>
    <para> The <command>globus-gram-audit</command> program support three database systems: MySQL,
      PostgreSQL, and SQLite. </para>
  </section></chapter>
