<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="gram5-performance-guide">
    <title>Scalability and Performance Recommendations</title>
    <indexterm type="gram5"><primary>performance guide</primary></indexterm>
    <para>This document includes recommendations for increasing the scalability
    and performance of GRAM5 in a Grid.</para>
    <section>
        <title>Server-side Recommendations</title>
        <indexterm type="gram5"><primary>performance guide</primary><secondary>server-side</secondary></indexterm>
       
        <section><title>Filesystem related settings</title>
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                The GRAM5 service stores job state for
                crash recovery on disk. By default, the 
                <filename><envar>$GLOBUS_LOCATION</envar>/tmp/gram_job_state</filename>
                directory is used for these files. If this path is located
                on a distributed file system mount, locking and updating
                the job state files can negatively effect performance.
                </para>
                <para>
                To configure GRAM5 to use a local disk for job state files,
                modify
                <filename><envar>$GLOBUS_LOCATION</envar>/etc/globus-job-manager.conf</filename>
                or
                <filename><envar>$GLOBUS_LOCATION</envar>/etc/grid-services/jobmanager-<replaceable>LRM</replaceable></filename>
                so that the argument to the <option>-state-file-dir</option>
                is a local directory path. That directory must be world
                writable with the "sticky bit" set (mode
                <literal>1777</literal>).
                </para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist> 
       </section>
        <section><title>LRM-related settings</title>
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                The GRAM5 service can use two different interfaces to obtain
                job state changes, polling and using the SEG. The default
                method is to poll the LRM via the GRAM5 script interface. This
                polling method is often less efficient than the SEG method and
                results in a higher load on the GRAM5 service node, even when
                all managed jobs are waiting in the queue for execution.
               </para>
               <para>The other method, uses a program implementing the SEG
               interface to generate LRM events which can be stored in a log
               file for job managers run by many different users to process.
               When this is used, the multiple job managers may detect
               job state changes without having to directly interact with the
               LRM.
               </para>
               <para>
               To enable the SEG to monitor jobs for a particular LRM, 
               <olink
               targetptr="gram5-admin-installing-pbs-lrm-adapter">install
               and configure</olink> the LRM-specific gram5 bundle, run the
               <olink
               targetptr="gram5-cmd-globus-job-manager-event-generator"><command>globus-job-manager-event-generator</command></olink>
               program on a node
               which can access the LRM interfaces needed by the LRM-specific
               SEG module, and <olink targetptr="gram5-Interface_Config_Frag-seg_module">configure the LRM-specific service instance to
               use the SEG</olink> to monitor jobs for state changes.
                </para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist> 
       </section>
     </section>
</chapter>
