<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" [

<!ENTITY GRAM "GRAM5" >
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
]>

<chapter id="gram5-developer-lrm-adapter-tutorial">
    <title>LRM Adapter Tutorial</title>

    <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para> 
        &GRAM; provides a resource-independent abstraction to remote job
        management.  The resource abstraction contains methods for
        job submission and cancelling, and a method for monitoring
        job state changes.  This set of tutorials describes how to implement
        and bundle all packages needed for a complete
        <glossterm>LRM Adapter</glossterm> interface for
        &GRAM;.
    </para>

    <para>
    For purposes of this tutorial, we will create a fake LRM adapter that
    pretends to run jobs, but in fact just keeps track of jobs and expires
    them after the job's <literal>max_wall_time</literal> expires. We'll
    call this LRM the <literal>fake</literal> LRM adapter.
    </para>
    </section>

    <section>
    <title>Parts of a &GRAM; LRM Adapter</title>
    <para>
    A &GRAM; LRM Adapter consists of a few parts which work together
    to provide a full interface between the &GRAM;
    <glossterm>Job Manager</glossterm> and the
    <glossterm>Local Resource Manager</glossterm>.
    These parts include:

    <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
        <term>RSL Validation File</term>
        <listitem><simpara>An option file which defines any custom RSL
        attributes which the LRM Adapter implements, or sets any custom 
        defaults for RSL attributes that the LRM processes. Defining new RSL
        attributes in this file allows the &GRAM; service to detect some sets
        of RSL errors without invoking the Perl LRM Adapter
        Module. For this example, the file will be called <filename>fake.rvf</filename>.</simpara></listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
        <term>Perl LRM Adapter Module</term>
        <listitem><simpara>A Perl module which implements the execution
        interface to the LRM. This module translates the 
        <glossterm>Resource Specification Language</glossterm> description
        of a job's requirements to a concrete way of starting the job
        on a particular LRM. For this example, this file will be called
        <filename>fake.pm</filename>.</simpara></listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
        <term>Configuration File</term>
        <listitem><simpara>The &GRAM; service implements a simple configuration
        file parser which can be used to provide a way to add site
        customizations to LRM Adapters. These files are usually shared between
        the Perl LRM Adapter Module and the Scheduler Event Generator
        Module. For this example, this file will be called
        <filename>fake.conf</filename>.</simpara></listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
        <term><glossterm>Gatekeeper</glossterm> Service File</term>
        <listitem><simpara>The Gatekeeper is a privileged service which
        authenticates and authorizes clients and then starts a 
        <glossterm>Job Manager</glossterm> process on their behalf. The
        Gatekeeper Service File contains the LRM-specific command-line options 
        to the job manager. For this example, this file will be called
        <filename>jobmanager-fork</filename>.</simpara></listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
        <term><glossterm>Scheduler Event Generator</glossterm> Module</term>
        <listitem><simpara>A dynamic object which parses LRM state and
        generates job state change events in a generic format for &GRAM;
        to consume. For this example, the SEG module will be called
        <filename>libglobus_seg_fake.so</filename>.</simpara></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    </para>
    </section>

    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        href="GRAM5_LRM_Adapter_Tutorial_RVF.xml"/>

    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        href="GRAM5_LRM_Adapter_Tutorial_Configuration.xml"/>

    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        href="GRAM5_LRM_Adapter_Tutorial_Perl.xml"/>

    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        href="GRAM5_LRM_Adapter_Tutorial_SEG.xml"/>

    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        href="GRAM5_LRM_Adapter_Tutorial_Changelog.xml"/>

</chapter>
