<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"[
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
]>
<chapter id="gridftp-configuring"><title>Configuring GridFTP</title>
  <indexterm type="gridftp">
    <primary>configuration interface for GridFTP</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm type="gridftp-howto">
    <primary>configuring GridFTP</primary>
  </indexterm>
  <section id="gridftp-config-overview"><title>GridFTP server configuration overview</title>
    <indexterm type="gridftp-howto">
      <primary>configuring GridFTP</primary>
      <secondary>overview</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>The configuration interface for GridFTP is the admin tool, <command><olink targetdoc="gridftpAdmin"
        targetptr="globus-gridftp-server"/></command>, which
      can be used with a configuration file and/or run-time options.</para><note>
      <para>Command line options and configuration file options may both be used, but the command
        line <emphasis>overrides</emphasis> the config file.</para>
    </note><para>The configuration file for the GridFTP <glossterm>server</glossterm> is read from
      the following locations, in the given order. Only the first file found will be loaded:<itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <simpara>Path specified with the <computeroutput>-c &lt;configfile&gt;</computeroutput>
            command line option.</simpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <simpara>
            <filename>$GLOBUS_LOCATION/etc/gridftp.conf</filename>
          </simpara>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <simpara>
            <filename>/etc/grid-security/gridftp.conf</filename>
          </simpara>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para><para>Options are one per line, with the format:
      <screen>&lt;option&gt; &lt;value&gt;</screen> If the value contains spaces, they should be
      enclosed in double-quotes ("). Flags or boolean options should only have a value of 0 or 1.
      Blank lines and lines beginning with # are ignored.</para><para>For example:
      <screen>  port 5000
  allow_anonymous 1
  anonymous_user bob
  banner "Welcome!"
      </screen></para><para>For
      complete command documentation including all options, see <command><olink targetdoc="gridftpAdmin"
        targetptr="globus-gridftp-server"/></command>.</para><para>This page includes information about
      general configuration of the GridFTP server. Security options are discussed <olink
        targetdoc="gridftpAdmin" targetptr="gridftp-admin-config-security">here</olink>, and more
      advanced configuration is described <olink targetdoc="gridftpAdmin"
        targetptr="gridftp-admin-advanced">here</olink>.</para></section><section
    id="gridftp-config-types"><title>Typical configuration</title>
    <indexterm type="gridftp">
      <primary>configuring GridFTP</primary>
      <secondary>typical</secondary>
    </indexterm>
    <para>The following describes a typical GridFTP configuration of the front end (control channel)
      and back end (data channels). For other alternatives that provide greater levels of security,
      see <olink targetdoc="gridftpAdmin" targetptr="gridftp-admin-advanced">Advanced
        Configuration</olink>.</para><para>By default, the data channel and control channel are
      separate socket connections within the same process. The client sends a command and waits to
      finish before issuing the next command. This is good for a single host, traditional-type user.
      If you have a single host and you want an ultra-reliable and light weight file transfer
      service, this is a good choice. This configuration is also good for testing
    purposes.</para></section><section id="gridftp-config-security-firewalls">
    <title>Firewall requirements</title>
    <!-- NOTE: any changes to this section need to be reproduced in GridFTP_Security_Considerations_Frag.xml -->
      <para>If the GridFTP server is behind a firewall:</para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Contact your network administrator to open up port 2811 (for GridFTP control channel
          connection) and a range of ports (for GridFTP data channel connections) for the incoming
          connections. If the firewall blocks the outgoing connections, open up a range of ports for
          outgoing connections as well.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Set the environment variable GLOBUS_TCP_PORT_RANGE:
          <screen>export GLOBUS_TCP_PORT_RANGE=min,max </screen> where
            <option>min</option>,<option>max</option> specify the port range that you have opened
          for the incoming connections on the firewall. This restricts the listening ports of the
          GridFTP server to this range. Recommended range is 1000 (e.g., 50000-51000) but it really
          depends on how much use you expect.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If you have a firewall blocking the outgoing connections and you have opened a range
          of ports, set the environment variable GLOBUS_TCP_SOURCE_RANGE:
          <screen>export GLOBUS_TCP_SOURCE_RANGE=min,max </screen> where
            <option>min</option>,<option>max</option> specify the port range that you have opened
          for the outgoing connections on the firewall. This restricts the
	  GridFTP server to bind to a local port in this range for outbound
	  connections.
          Recommended range is twice the range used for
          GLOBUS_TCP_PORT_RANGE, because if parallel TCP streams are used for transfers, the
          listening port would remain the same for each connection but the connecting port would be
          different for each connection.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <note>
      <para>If the server is behind NAT, the <computeroutput>--data-interface &lt;real
          ip/hostname&gt;</computeroutput> option needs to be used on the server.</para>
    </note>
      <!-- NOTE: the three client-firewall elements (-intro, -config and -moreinfo) are being pulled into the User's Guide -->
      <para id="gridftp-client-firewall-intro">If the GridFTP <emphasis>client</emphasis> is behind a firewall:</para>
      
      <!-- NOTE: the three client-firewall elements (-intro, -config and -moreinfo) are being pulled into the User's Guide -->
      <orderedlist id="gridftp-client-firewall-config">
      <listitem>
        <para>Contact your network administrator to open up a range of ports (for GridFTP data
          channel connections) for the incoming connections. If the firewall blocks the outgoing
          connections, open up a range of ports for outgoing connections as well.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Set the environment variable GLOBUS_TCP_PORT_RANGE
          <screen>export GLOBUS_TCP_PORT_RANGE=min,max </screen> where min,max specify the port
          range that you have opened for the incoming connections on the firewall. This restricts
          the listening ports of the GridFTP client to this range. Recommended range is 1000 (e.g.,
          50000-51000) but it really depends on how much use you expect.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>If you have a firewall blocking the outgoing connections and you have opened a range
          of (local) ports, set the environment variable GLOBUS_TCP_SOURCE_RANGE:
          <screen>export GLOBUS_TCP_PORT_RANGE=min,max </screen> where min,max specify the port
          range that you have opened for the outgoing connections on the
	  firewall. This restricts the GridFTP client to bind to a local port in
	  this range for
          outbound connections. Recommended range is twice the
          range used for GLOBUS_TCP_PORT_RANGE, because if parallel TCP streams are used for
          transfers, the listening port would remain the same for each connection but the connecting
          port would be different for each connection.</para>
      </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      
      <!-- NOTE: the three client-firewall elements (-intro, -config and -moreinfo) are being pulled into the User's Guide -->
    <para id="gridftp-client-firewall-moreinfo">Additional information on Globus Toolkit Firewall Requirements is available <ulink
        url="http://www.globus.org/toolkit/security/firewalls/">here</ulink>.</para>
  </section><section id="gridftp-admin-config-security">
    <title>Configuring Security for GridFTP</title>
    <para>There are many security options in GridFTP ranging from no security to higher security via
      GSI .</para>
    <section id="gridftp-admin-config-security-anonymous"><title>Anonymous mode</title>
      <indexterm type="gridftp-howto">
        <primary>configuring GridFTP</primary>
        <secondary>security</secondary>
        <tertiary>anonymous mode</tertiary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>Anonymous mode (using the <option>-aa</option> option) allows any user with an FTP
        client to read and write (and delete) files that the server process can similarly access (it
        is also a quick way to test that your server works).</para>
        <screen><prompt role="globus"/><command>globus-gridftp-server -aa</command>
<computeroutput>Server listening at 127.0.0.1:58806</computeroutput></screen>
        <warning>
        <para>When the server is run in this way, anyone who can connect to the server will posses
          all the same rights as the user that the process is run as (directly or via
            <option>-anonymous-user</option>). If using this mode intentionally for open access, it
          is best to run under a dedicated account with limited filesystem permissions. You can also
          use the option below to disable FTP commands such as STOR, ESTO, DELE, RDEL, RNTO, etc to
          make sure that users can only read from the server and not write to it.
          <screen> -disable-command-list &lt;string&gt;</screen> Where &lt;string&gt; represents a
          comma separated list of client commands that will be disabled. Default: not set. </para>
      </warning></section>
    <section id="gridftp-admin-config-security-userpw"><title>Username/password</title>
      <indexterm type="gridftp-howto">
        <primary>configuring GridFTP</primary>
        <secondary>security</secondary>
        <tertiary>username/password</tertiary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>If you trust your network and want a minimal amount of security, you can run the
        globus-gridftp-server with clear text passwords. This security model is the one originally
        introduced in RFC959.</para><warning>
        <para>We do not recommend it for long running servers open to the internet.</para>
      </warning><section>
        <title>Create password file</title>
        <para>To run the server in clear text password mode, we first need to create a password file
          dedicated to it. The format of the password file is the same as standard system password
          files; however, it is ill-advised to use a system password file. To create an entry in a
          GridFTP password file, run the following commands:</para>
        <screen><prompt role="globus"/><command>touch pwfile</command>
<prompt role="globus"/><command>gridftp-password.pl &gt;&gt; pwfile</command>
<computeroutput>Password:</computeroutput></screen>
        <para>This will ask you for a password and then create an entry in the password file for the
          current user name and the given password. Take a look at the file created. You will notice
          that the password you typed in is not in the file in a clear text form. We have run it
          though a one way hash algorithm before storing it in the file.</para>
      </section><section>
        <title>Run the server in password mode</title>
        <para>Simply start the server pointing it at the password file you just created.</para>
        <screen><prompt role="globus"/><command>globus-gridftp-server -password-file  /full/path/of/pwfile</command>
<computeroutput>Server listening at 127.0.0.1:5555</computeroutput></screen>
      </section><section>
        <title>Make a transfer</title>
        <para>To run globus-url-copy with the password, use the following syntax:</para>
        <screen><prompt role="globus"/><command>globus-url-copy file:///etc/group ftp://<replaceable>username</replaceable>:<replaceable>pw</replaceable>@localhost:5000/tmp/group</command></screen>
      </section></section>
    <section id="gridftp-admin-config-security-sshftp"><title>SSHFTP (GridFTP-over-SSH)</title>
      <indexterm type="gridftp-howto">
        <primary>configuring GridFTP</primary>
        <secondary>security</secondary>
        <tertiary>over SSH</tertiary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>This type of security introduces the sshftp control channel (frontend) protocol. This is
        a very simple means of obtaining strong security on the control channel only (the data
        channel is <emphasis>not</emphasis> authenticated). With this approach, you can run a
        GridFTP transfer anywhere that you can ssh. <filename>sshftp://</filename> leverages the
        ubiquitous ssh/sshd programs to form control channel connections much in the same way that
        inetd forms connections.</para><section>
        <title>Configure Server for SSH GridFTP Support</title>
        <para>Every host that wishes to run a <command>globus-gridftp-server</command> which can
          accept <filename>sshftp://</filename> connections must run the following command as
          root:</para>
        <screen><prompt role="globus"/><command>globus-gridftp-server-enable-sshftp</command></screen>
        <para>In the absence of root access, a user can configure the server to allow <filename
            >sshftp://</filename> connections for that user only with the following command:</para>
        <screen><prompt role="globus"/><command>globus-gridftp-server-enable-sshftp -nonroot</command></screen>
        <para> 
	  The above command creates a file named 'sshftp' in
	  '/etc/grid-security' (if run as root) or in '$HOME/.globus' (if run as
	  nonroot).   You may edit this file to set gridftp commandline options
	  or environment variables such as GLOBUS_TCP_PORT_RANGE, but you can
	  also set those options in the config file.
	  </para>
      </section><section>
        <title>Performing <filename>sshftp://</filename> Transfers</title>
        <para>In this case, a <command>globus-gridftp-server</command> does not need to be running.
          The server will be started via the sshd program. Therefore, the hostname and port should
          be that of the sshd server. Run <command>globus-url-copy</command> just as you have
          before; simply change <filename>ftp://</filename> to <filename
          >sshftp://</filename>.</para>
        <screen><prompt role="globus"/><command>globus-url-copy -v file:/etc/group sshftp://127.0.0.1/tmp/group</command>
<prompt role="globus"/><command>globus-url-copy -list sshftp://127.0.0.1/tmp/</command></screen>
      </section></section>
    <section id="gridftp-admin-gsiftp"><title>GSIFTP</title>
      <indexterm type="gridftp-howto">
        <primary>configuring GridFTP</primary>
        <secondary>security</secondary>
        <tertiary>gsiftp</tertiary>
      </indexterm>
      <para>This security option can be the most involved to set up, but provides the most security.
        It requires setting up GSI security as described in the GT Installation Guide here: <olink
          targetdoc="gtadmin" targetptr="gtadmin-basic-security"/>. </para><para>Once GSI has been
        set up (host and user credentials are valid, the gridmap file is updated and you've run
        grid-proxy-init to create a proxy certificate), you simply run the GridFTP server:</para><screen>globus-gridftp-server</screen><note>
        <para>If run as <computeroutput>root</computeroutput>, it will pick up the host cert; if
          not, it will pick up the user cert.</para>
      </note><para>Now you are ready to perform a GSI-authenticated transfer:</para><screen>globus-url-copy &lt;-s subject&gt; src_url dst_url</screen><note>
        <para>The subject option is only needed if the server was not started as root.</para>
      </note><section id="gridftp-admin-daemon_mode"><title>Running in daemon mode</title>
        <indexterm type="gridftp-howto">
          <primary>running in daemon mode</primary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm type="gridftp">
          <primary>admin scenarios</primary>
          <secondary>running in daemon mode</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <para>The server should generally be run as root in daemon mode, although it is possible to
          run it as a user (see below). When run as root you will need to have a <olink
            targetdoc="gtadmin" targetptr="gtadmin-basic-host">host
          certificate</olink>.</para><para>Run the
          server:</para><screen>globus-gridftp-server &lt; -s | -S &gt; &lt;args&gt;</screen><para>where:</para><variablelist
          termlength="100pt">
          <varlistentry>
            <term>-s</term>
            <listitem>
              <simpara>Runs in the foreground (this is the default mode).</simpara>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>-S</term>
            <listitem>
              <simpara>Detaches from the terminal and runs in the background.</simpara>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist><para>The following additional steps may be required when running as a user
          other than root (for more details, review <olink targetdoc="gtadmin"
            targetptr="gtadmin-basic-security"/>): <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <simpara>Create a <filename>~/.gridmap</filename> file, containing the DNs of any
                clients you wish to allow, mapped to the current username.</simpara>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <simpara>Create a proxy with <command>grid-proxy-init</command>.</simpara>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para></section><section id="gridftp-admin-inetd"><title>Running under
          inetd or xinetd</title>
        <indexterm type="gridftp-howto">
          <primary>deploying</primary>
          <secondary>running under inetd or xinetd</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <indexterm type="gridftp">
          <primary>deploying</primary>
          <secondary>running under inetd or xinetd</secondary>
        </indexterm>
        <note>
          <para>We also feature a user-configurable, super-server daemon plugin called GFork. Click
              <olink targetdoc="gridftpAdmin" targetptr="gridftp-admin-gfork-master">here</olink>
            for more information.</para>
        </note><section>
          <title>Set up xinetd/inetd config file</title>
          <note>
            <para>The service name used (gsiftp in this case) should be defined in <computeroutput
                >/etc/services</computeroutput> with the desired port.</para>
          </note>
          <para>Here is a sample GridFTP server xinetd config entry in <filename
              >/etc/xinetd.conf</filename>:
            <screen>service gsiftp
              {
              instances               = 100
              socket_type             = stream
              wait                    = no
              user                    = root
              env                     += GLOBUS_LOCATION=(globus_location)
              env                     += LD_LIBRARY_PATH=(globus_location)/lib
              server                  = (globus_location)/sbin/globus-gridftp-server
              server_args             = -i
              log_on_success          += DURATION
              nice                    = 10
              disable                 = no
              }</screen>
            Here is a sample gridftp server inetd config entry in <filename
              >/etc/inetd.conf</filename> (read as a single line):
            <screen>
              gsiftp   stream   tcp   nowait   root   /usr/bin/env env   \
              GLOBUS_LOCATION=(globus_location)                      \
              LD_LIBRARY_PATH=(globus_location)/lib                  \ 
              (globus_location)/sbin/globus-gridftp-server -i
            </screen></para>
          <note>
            <para>On Mac OS X, you must set DYLD_LIBRARY_PATH instead of LD_LIBRARY_PATH in the
              above examples. </para>
          </note>
          <note>
            <para>You should NOT include USERID in the log lines. See <olink
                targetdoc="gridftpAdmin" targetptr="gridftp-troubleshooting-latency"/> for more
              information.</para>
          </note>
        </section><section>
          <title>globus-gridftp-server -i</title>
          <para>Use the <option>-i</option> commandline option with <command
              >globus-gridftp-server</command>: <screen>globus-gridftp-server -i</screen></para>
        </section></section>
      <section id="gridftp-admin-launchd"><title>Running under launchd</title>
        
        <para>launchd is used to start services in the system Mac OS X 10.4 (Tiger) and newer, and is also available as a port to FreeBSD.</para>
        
        <para>Here is a <ulink url="http://www.globus.org/toolkit/docs/{$shortversion}/{$version}/gridftp/globus.gridftp.plist">sample</ulink> configuration file for launchd to start the server:</para>
        
        <programlisting><xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" parse="text" href="globus.gridftp.plist"/></programlisting>
        <para>Provided that the configuration file is stored in <filename>/System/Library/LaunchDaemons/globus.gridftp.plist</filename>, the following command starts the GridFTP server:</para>
        
        <screen><command>launchctl load /System/Library/LaunchDaemons/globus.griftp.plist</command></screen>
        
        <para>The server will be started automatically with a system, unless the value of the key 'Disabled' is changed from <code>&lt;false/&gt;</code> to <code>&lt;true/&gt;</code>.</para>
      </section>
    
    </section>
    <section id="gridftp-admin-user-pems">
      <title>User permissions</title>
      <para>Users are mapped to a local account on the server machine and file permissions are
        handled by the operating systems. In the anonymous mode, users that connect to the server
        will posses all the same rights as the user that the server process is run as (directly or
        via -anonymous-user).</para>
      <para>In case of username/password authentication, the users are mapped to the uid
        corresponding to the username in the GridFTP password file and the access permissions for
        the users is same as that of the UID that they are mapped to. If SSH based authentication is
        used, upon successful authentication, SSHD maps users to a local account and the GridFTP
        server is run as the mapped local user. The access permissions are the same as that of the
        mapped local user.</para>
      <para>If GSI is used, upon successful authentication an authorization callout is invoked to
        (a) verify authorization and (b) determine the local user id as which the request should be
        executed. This callout is linked dynamically. Globus GridFTP provides an implementation that
        supports a Globus "gridmapfile". Sites can also provide alternative implementations. Server
        does a setuid to the local user id as determined by the authorization callout and the access
        permissions are the same as that of the local user id.</para>
      <para>GridFTP server provides an option to disable certain FTP commands:
        <screen> -disable-command-list &lt;string&gt;</screen> Where &lt;string&gt; represents a
        comma separated list of client commands that will be disabled. Default: not set.</para>
    </section>
  </section><section>
    <title><command>globus-gridftp-server</command> quickstart</title>
    <para>The following is a quick guide to running the server and using the client:</para>
    <para>Look through the list of options for globus-gridftp-server:</para>
    <screen>globus-gridftp-server --help</screen>
    <para>Start the server in anonymous mode (discussed more fully <olink targetdoc="gridftpAdmin"
        targetptr="gridftp-admin-config-security-anonymous">here</olink>):</para>
    <screen>globus-gridftp-server -control-interface 127.0.0.1 -aa -p 5000</screen>
    <para>where: <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>–control-interface</term>
          <listitem>
            <simpara>is the hostname or IP address of the interface to listen for control
              connections on <!-- fixme need to find better syntax for this sentence -->. This
              option is only needed here as a rudimentary means of security for this simple example.
            </simpara>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>–aa</term>
          <listitem>
            <simpara>enables anonymous mode</simpara>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>–p</term>
          <listitem>
            <simpara>indicates on which port the server listens.</simpara>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist></para>
    <para>Run a two party transfer with client:</para>
    <screen>globus-url-copy -v file:///etc/group ftp://localhost:5000/tmp/group</screen>
    <para>Run 3rd party transfer:</para>
    <screen>globus-url-copy -v ftp://localhost:<replaceable>port</replaceable>/etc/group ftp://localhost:<replaceable>port</replaceable>/tmp/group2</screen>
    <para>Experiment with -dbg, and -vb options for debugging and checking the performance of your
      setup:</para>
    <screen>globus-url-copy -dbg file:///etc/group ftp://localhost:5000/tmp/group</screen>
    <screen>globus-url-copy -vb file:///dev/zero ftp://localhost:5000/dev/null</screen>
    <para>where:</para>
    <variablelist id="debugging-options">
      <varlistentry>
        <term><option> -dbg</option></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>A useful option when something is not working. It results in a GridFTP control
            channel protocol dump (along with other useful information) to stderr. If you understand
            the GridFTP protocol, or you have ambition to understand it, this can be a very useful
            tool to discover various problems in your setup such as overloaded servers and
            firewalls. When submitting a bug report or asking a question on the support email lists
            one should always send along the -dbg output.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><option>-vb</option></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Provides a type of progress bar of the user to observe the rate at which their
            transfer is progressing.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>Ctrl-c - Kill the server.</para>
    <note>
      <para>There are many possible options and configurations with <command
          >globus-gridftp-server</command>. For some guidelines on setting it up for your situation,
        see <olink targetdoc="gridftpAdmin" targetptr="gridftp-admin-tuning"/>.</para>
    </note>
  </section>
  <section>
      <title>Enabling File Sharing with Globus Sharing Service</title>
      <para>To enable file sharing using <ulink
              url="https://www.globus.org/researchers/plus-plans">Globus
	      Sharing</ulink>, you have to add the <ulink
	      url="../securityd2b.tar.gz">Globus Sharing CA
	      certificates</ulink> to your trusted certificates directory
	      (/etc/grid-security/certificates) and use '-sharing-dn' option in the server
	      as follows:
<screen><prompt role="globus"/><command>globus-gridftp-server -sharing-dn
"/C=US/O=Globus Consortium/OU=Globus Connect User/CN=__transfer__"</command>
</screen>
	and use '-sharing-rp' option to restrict the file paths allowed for
	sharing:
<screen><prompt role="globus"/><command>globus-gridftp-server -sharing-rp &lt;path&gt; </command>
</screen></para>
</section>
  </chapter>
