<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<section id="gridftp-security-considerations"><title>Security Considerations </title>
    <indexterm type="gridftp">
        <primary>security considerations for GridFTP</primary>
    </indexterm>
    <section id="gridftp-security-config">
        <title>Ways to configure your server</title>
        <para>There are various ways to configure your GridFTP server that provide varying levels of security. For more information, see <olink targetdoc="gridftpAdmin"/>.</para>
       
    </section>
    <section id="gridftp-security-firewalls">
        <title>Firewall requirements</title>
        <!-- NOTE: any changes to this section need to be reproduced in GridFTP_Interface_Config_Frag.xml -->
        <para> If the GridFTP <emphasis>server</emphasis> is behind a firewall:</para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Contact your network administrator to open up port 2811 (for GridFTP control
                    channel connection) and a range of ports (for GridFTP data channel connections)
                    for the incoming connections. If the firewall blocks the outgoing connections,
                    open up a range of ports for outgoing connections as well.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Set the environment variable GLOBUS_TCP_PORT_RANGE:
                    <screen>export GLOBUS_TCP_PORT_RANGE=min,max </screen> where
                        <option>min</option>,<option>max</option> specify the port range that you
                    have opened for the incoming connections on the firewall. This restricts the
                    listening ports of the GridFTP server to this range. Recommended range is 1000
                    (e.g., 50000-51000) but it really depends on how much use you expect.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>If you have a firewall blocking the outgoing connections and you have opened a
                    range of (local) ports, set the environment variable GLOBUS_TCP_SOURCE_RANGE:
                    <screen>export GLOBUS_TCP_SOURCE_RANGE=min,max </screen> where
                        <option>min</option>,<option>max</option> specify the port range that you
                    have opened for the outgoing connections on the firewall.
		    This restricts the GridFTP server to bind to a local port in this
		    range for outbound connections. Recommended range is twice
                    the range used for GLOBUS_TCP_PORT_RANGE, because if parallel TCP streams are
                    used for transfers, the listening port would remain the same for each connection
                    but the connecting port would be different for each connection.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <note>
            <para>If the server is behind NAT, the <computeroutput>--data-interface &lt;real
                    ip/hostname&gt;</computeroutput> option needs to be used on the server.</para>
        </note>
        <para>If the GridFTP <emphasis>client</emphasis> is behind a firewall:</para>
        <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>Contact your network administrator to open up a range of ports (for GridFTP
                    data channel connections) for the incoming connections. If the firewall blocks
                    the outgoing connections, open up a range of ports for outgoing connections as
                    well.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>Set the environment variable GLOBUS_TCP_PORT_RANGE
                    <screen>export GLOBUS_TCP_PORT_RANGE=min,max </screen> where min,max specify the
                    port range that you have opened for the incoming connections on the firewall.
                    This restricts the listening ports of the GridFTP client to this range.
                    Recommended range is 1000 (e.g., 50000-51000) but it really depends on how much
                    use you expect.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>If you have a firewall blocking the outgoing connections and you have opened a
                    range of ports, set the environment variable GLOBUS_TCP_SOURCE_RANGE:
                    <screen>export GLOBUS_TCP_PORT_RANGE=min,max </screen> where min,max specify the
                    port range that you have opened for the outgoing connections on the firewall.
                    This restricts the GridFTP client to bind to a local port
		    in this range for outbound connections.
                    Recommended range is twice the range used for GLOBUS_TCP_PORT_RANGE, because if
                    parallel TCP streams are used for transfers, the listening port would remain the
                    same for each connection but the connecting port would be different for each
                    connection.</para>
            </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <para>Additional information on Globus Toolkit Firewall Requirements is available <ulink
                url="http://www.globus.org/toolkit/security/firewalls/">here</ulink>.</para>
    </section>
</section>
