<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">

<section id="gridftp-migrating-GT3">
    <title>Migrating GridFTP from GT3</title>
<para>  If you are running GT 3.0.0 or greater, the migration for GridFTP is relatively painless.  There were only new 
    features added.  No changes were made to the existing protocol or APIs, so any existing <glossterm>client</glossterm> or application 
    built using our client APIs will work unchanged.  You may install new clients and servers on an as-opportunity-permits basis and will have no problems.  Any combination of old/new client/server will work.</para>
    
    <para>To upgrade your server, either install it in a $GLOBUS_LOCATION different than the GT 3 installation (either as 
    part of an entire GT 4 installation or by doing just <computeroutput>make gridftp</computeroutput>).  Alternately, you can statically link the new 
    server to avoid versioning issues and replace the existing executable.  The configuration files are very 
    different, so you will need to update the configuration.</para>
    
<para>    To upgrade your client, simply build the client and use the new client as you would the old one. </para>
    
    <para>Below is a list of new functionality available in GT 3.2 and higher (note that the MLST/MLSD feature is used by 
    RFT in GT 3.2 and higher and is required if you want to be able to specify a directory to move):</para>
    
<para>    New Functionality in 3.2:</para>
<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>
Server Improvements
    <itemizedlist>    
    <listitem><simpara>Structured File Info</simpara></listitem>
    <listitem><simpara>MLST, MLSD</simpara></listitem>
    <listitem><simpara>checksum support</simpara></listitem>
    <listitem><simpara>chmod support</simpara></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>    
</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem><para>
    globus-url-copy changes
    <itemizedlist>    
    <listitem><simpara>File globbing support</simpara></listitem>
    <listitem><simpara>Recursive dir moves</simpara></listitem>
    <listitem><simpara>RFC 1738 support</simpara></listitem>
    <listitem><simpara>Control of restart</simpara></listitem>
    <listitem><simpara>Control of DC security</simpara></listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
</para>
    </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
</section>