<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="gridftp-api-summary"><title>API Summary</title>
  <indexterm type="gridftp"><primary>API information for GridFTP</primary></indexterm>
  <section>
    <title>Programming Model Overview</title>
    <para>The Globus FTP Client library provides a convenient way of accessing files on remote FTP
      servers. In addition to supporting the basic FTP protocol, the FTP Client library supports
      several security and performance extensions to make FTP more suitable for Grid applications.
      These extensions are described in the <ulink
        url="http://www.globus.org/alliance/publications/papers/GFD-R.0201.pdf">GridFTP Protocol
        document</ulink>.</para>
    <para>In addition to protocol support for grid applications, the FTP Client library provides a
        <ulink
          url="http://www.globus.org/api/c-globus-${version}/globus_ftp_client/html/group__globus__ftp__client__plugins.html"
        >plugin architecture</ulink> for installing application or grid-specific fault recovery and
      performance tuning algorithms within the library. Application writers may then target their
      code toward the FTP Client library and, by simply enabling the appropriate plugins, easily
      tune their application to run it on a different grid.</para>
    <para>All applications which use the Globus FTP Client API must include the header file
        <filename>globus_ftp_client.h</filename> and activate the <ulink
          url="http://www.globus.org/api/c-globus-{$version}/globus_ftp_client/html/group__globus__ftp__client__activation.html"
        >GLOBUS_FTP_CLIENT_MODULE</ulink>.</para>
    <para>To use the Globus FTP Client API, one must create an <ulink
      url="http://www.globus.org/api/c-globus-{$version}/globus_ftp_client/html/group__globus__ftp__client__handle.html"
        >FTP Client handle</ulink>. This structure contains: <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>context information about FTP operations which are being executed,</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>a cache of FTP control and data connections, and</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>information about plugins which are being used.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist> The specifics of the connection caching and plugins are found in the "<ulink
        url="http://www.globus.org/api/c-globus-{$version}/globus_ftp_client/html/group__globus__ftp__client__handleattr.html"
        >Handle Attributes</ulink>" section of the API documentation.</para>
    <para>Once the handle is created, one may begin transferring files or doing other FTP operations
      by calling the functions in the "<ulink
        url="http://www.globus.org/api/c-globus-{$version}/globus_ftp_client/html/group__globus__ftp__client__operations.html"
        >FTP Operations</ulink>" section of the API documentation. In addition to whole-file
      transfers, the API supports partial file transfers, restarting transfers from a known point,
      and various FTP directory management commands. All FTP operations may have a set of
      attributes, defined in the operationattr section, associated with them to tune various FTP
      parameters. The data structures and functions needed to restart a file transfer are described
      in the "<ulink
        url="http://www.globus.org/api/c-globus-{$version}/globus_ftp_client/html/group__globus__ftp__client__restart__marker.html"
        >Restart Markers</ulink>" section of the API documentation. For operations which require the
      user to send to or receive data from an FTP <glossterm>server</glossterm> they must call the
      functions described in the "globus_ftp_client_data" section of the manual.</para>
    <para>The globus_ftp_control library provides low-level services needed to implement FTP clients
      and servers. The API provided is protocol specific. The data transfer portion of this API
      provides support for the standard data methods described in the FTP Specification as well as
      extensions for parallel, striped, and partial data transfer. </para>
  </section><section>
    <title>Component API</title>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <simpara><ulink
            url="http://www.globus.org/api/c-globus-{$version}/globus_ftp_client/html/index.html">C
            Client Library API</ulink></simpara>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <simpara><ulink
            url="http://www.globus.org/api/c-globus-{$version}/globus_ftp_control/html/index.html">C
            Control Library API</ulink></simpara>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>For information on the internationalization API, see <olink targetdoc="ccommonlibPI"
        targetptr="ccommonlib-apis"/>. </para>
  </section></chapter>
