<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"[
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
]>
<chapter id="gridftp-troubleshooting"><title>Troubleshooting</title>
    <indexterm type="gridftp-howto"><primary>troubleshooting for GridFTP</primary></indexterm>
    <indexterm type="gridftp"><primary>troubleshooting for GridFTP</primary></indexterm>
    <para>If you are having problems using the GridFTP <glossterm>server</glossterm>, try the steps
        listed below. If you have an error, try checking the server logs if you have access to them.
        By default, the server logs to stderr, unless it is running from inetd, or its execution
        mode is detached, in which case logging is disabled by default. </para><para> The command
        line options -d , -log-level, -L and -logdir can affect where logs will be written, as can
        the configuration file options log_single and log_unique. See the <olink
            targetdoc="gridftpPI" targetptr="globus-gridftp-server"/> for more information on these
            and other configuration options.</para>
   <!-- <para>For a list of common errors in GT, see <olink
    targetdoc="gtuser" targetptr="errors"/>.</para> -->
    <xi:include
        href="GridFTP_Errors_Frag.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/><section>
        <title>Establish control channel connection</title>
        <para>Verify that you can establish a control channel connection and that the server has
            started successfully by telnetting to the port on which the server is running: </para>
        <screen>% telnet localhost 2811
                Trying 127.0.0.1...
                Connected to localhost.
                Escape character is '^]'.
                220 GridFTP Server mldev.mcs.anl.gov 2.0 (gcc32dbg, 1113865414-1) ready.</screen>
        <para>If you see anything other than a 220 banner such as the one above, the server has not
            started correctly.</para>
        <para>Verify that there are no configuration files being unexpectedly loaded from
            /etc/grid-security/gridftp.conf or $GLOBUS_LOCATION/etc/gridftp.conf. If those files
            exist, and you did not intend for them to be used, rename them to .save, or specify -c
            none on the command line and try again.</para>
        <para>If you can log into the machine where the server is, try running the server from the
            command line with only the -s option: </para>
        <screen>$GLOBUS_LOCATION/sbin/globus-gridftp-server -s</screen>
        <para>The server will print the port it is listening on: </para>
        <screen>Server listening at gridftp.mcs.anl.gov:57764</screen>
        <para>Now try and telnet to that port. If you still do not get the banner listed above,
            something is preventing the socket connection. Check firewalls, tcp-wrapper, etc.</para>
        <para>If you now get a correct banner, add -p 2811 (you will have to disable (x)inetd on
            port 2811 if you are using them or you will get port already in use):</para>
        <screen>$GLOBUS_LOCATION/sbin/globus-gridftp-server -s -p 2811</screen>
        <para>Now telnet to port 2811. If this does not work, something is blocking port 2811. Check
            firewalls, tcp-wrapper, etc.</para>
        <para>If this works correctly then re-enable your normal server, but remove all options but
            -i, -s, or -S.</para>
        <para>Now telnet to port 2811. If this does not work, something is wrong with your service
            configuration. Check /etc/services and (x)inetd config, have (x)inetd restarted, etc.</para>
        <para>If this works, begin adding options back one at a time, verifying that you can telnet
            to the server after each option is added. Continue this till you find the problem or get
            all the options you want. </para>
        <para>At this point, you can establish a control connection. Now try running
            globus-url-copy.</para>
    </section><section>
        <title>Try running globus-url-copy</title>
        <para>Once you've verified that you can establish a control connection, try to make a
            transfer using globus-url-copy.</para>
        <para>If you are doing a <glossterm>client</glossterm>/server transfer (one of your URLs has
                <filename>file:</filename> in it) then try:</para>
        <screen>globus-url-copy -vb -dbg gsiftp://host.server.running.on/dev/zero file:///dev/null</screen>
        <para>This will run until you control-c the transfer. If that works, reverse the direction:</para>
        <screen>globus-url-copy -vb -dbg file:///dev/zero gsiftp://host.server.running.on/dev/null</screen>
        <para>Again, this will run until you control-c the transfer.</para>
        <para>If you are doing a <glossterm baseform="third party transfers">third party
            transfer</glossterm>, run this command:</para>
        <screen>globus-url-copy -vb -dbg gsiftp://host.server1.on/dev/zero gsiftp://host.server2.on/dev/null</screen>
        <para>Again, this will run until you control-c the transfer.</para>
        <para>If the above transfers work, try your transfer again. If it fails, you likely have
            some sort of file permissions problem, typo in a file name, etc.</para>
    </section><section>
        <title>If your server starts...</title>
        <para>If the server has started correctly, and your problem is with a security failure or
            gridmap lookup failure, verify that you have security configured properly <olink
                targetdoc="gtadmin" targetptr="gtadmin-basic-security">here</olink>.</para>
        <para>If the server is running and your client successfully authenticates but has a problem
            at some other time during the session, please ask for help on <ulink
                url="http://dev.globus.org/wiki/Mailing_Lists">gt-user@globus.org</ulink>. When you
            send mail or submit bugs, please always include as much of the following information as
            possible:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <simpara>Specs on all hosts involved (OS, processor, RAM, etc).</simpara>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <simpara>globus-url-copy -version</simpara>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <simpara>globus-url-copy -versions </simpara>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <simpara>Output from the telnet test above.</simpara>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <simpara>The actual command line you ran with -dbg added. Don't worry if the output
                    gets long.</simpara>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <simpara>Check that you are getting a FQDN and /etc/hosts that is sane.</simpara>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <simpara>The server configuration and setup (/etc/services entries, (x)inetd
                    configs, etc.).</simpara>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <simpara> Any relevant lines from the server logs (not the entire log
                please).</simpara>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section><section id="gridftp-troubleshooting-latency">
        <title>High latency for GridFTP server connections</title>
        <para> If you run GridFTP servers via Xinetd and notice high latency for connections and/or
            transfers, check if <filename>/etc/xinetd.conf</filename> or the gsiftp service
            configuration inside <filename>/etc/xinetd.d</filename> is set to log USERID as follows:
            <screen>log_on_success += USERID
log_on_failure += USERID</screen></para>
        <para>Such a configuration tells Xinetd to log the remote user using the method defined in
            RFC 1413, which causes an ident client to attempt to query the machine that the
            connection is coming from before the service will run. Even when this succeeds, the
            response can't be trusted, and more often than not it is rejected or simply dropped
            (which results in the longest delays) by the remote firewall.</para>
        <para>Latency can be reduced by making sure Xinetd does <emphasis>not</emphasis> log the
            USERID.</para>
    </section></chapter>
