<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"
[

<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "../../xinclude.mod" >
%xinclude;

]>
<book id="gsiopensshAdmin">
<title>GT <replaceable role="entity">version</replaceable> GSI-OpenSSH: System Administrator's Guide</title>
<titleabbrev>System Administrator's Guide</titleabbrev>

  <bookinfo id="gsiopenssh-admin-introduction"><abstract><title>Introduction</title>
<para>
This guide contains advanced configuration information for system administrators
  working with GSI-OpenSSH. It provides references to information
  on procedures typically performed by system administrators, including installation,
  configuring, deploying, and testing the installation.</para>
<para>  <important>
    <simpara> This information is in addition to the basic Globus Toolkit prerequisite, 
      overview, installation, security configuration instructions in <olink targetdoc="gtadmin"/>.  
      Read through this guide before continuing!</simpara>  
  </important></para>
<para>This guide is meant solely to cover the GSI aspects of GSI-OpenSSH,
  and is not meant to be a full manual for OpenSSH itself.
  Please refer to the <ulink url="http://www.openssh.org/">OpenSSH Home Page</ulink> for
  general documentation for OpenSSH.</para></abstract>
</bookinfo>
  <chapter id="gsiopenssh-admin-installing"><title>Building and Installing</title>
  <para>GSI-OpenSSH is built and installed as part of a default GT <replaceable role="entity">version</replaceable> installation.
  For basic installation
  instructions, see <olink targetdoc="gtadmin"/>. No extra installation steps are required
  for this component.
</para>

    <section id="gsiopenssh-admin-installing-configure-options" xreflabel="Optional Build-Time Configuration for GSI-OpenSSH"><title>Optional Build-Time Configuration</title>
<para>
You can optionally pass build-time configure options to the
GSI-OpenSSH package using the --with-gsiopensshargs option when
  running configure for your GT <replaceable role="entity">version</replaceable> installation.
For example:
<blockquote><para>
<screen>./configure --prefix=$HOME/globus 
      --with-gsiopensshargs="--with-pam"</screen>
</para></blockquote>
No options are typically needed for client-only
installations, but options are often needed for full server
functionality.
The following lists suggested options for different platforms.

<variablelist id="gsiopenssh-admin-configure">
    <varlistentry>
        <term>Linux</term>
        <listitem><simpara><literal>--with-pam --with-md5-passwords --with-tcp-wrappers</literal></simpara></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
        <term>Solaris</term>
        <listitem><simpara><literal>--with-pam --with-md5-passwords --with-tcp-wrappers++</literal></simpara></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</para>

<note><para>Note: If you enable PAM support with the --with-pam configuration
option, be sure to also set "UsePAM yes" in
$GLOBUS_LOCATION/etc/ssh/sshd_config after installation.
</para></note>

<para>
If you have an already configured and installed system-wide SSHD and
you would like your build of GSI-OpenSSH to behave similarly,
investigate the configure options available in GSI-OpenSSH and select
those options that would add the functionality that your current SSHD
possesses.  Be aware that since GSI-OpenSSH is based on OpenSSH, the
standard set of functionality is turned on by default.
</para>

<para>
<emphasis>Please do not attempt to override the following options:</emphasis>
</para>
<screen>
--prefix
--sysconfdir
--with-globus
--with-globus-flavor
--with-ssl-dir
</screen>
</section>

<section id="gsiopenssh-admin-installing-openssh-only"><title>Building and Installing only GSI-OpenSSH</title>
<para>If you wish to install GSI-OpenSSH without installing the rest
  of the Globus Toolkit, follow the instructions in <olink targetdoc="gtadmin"/> 
  with the following changes.  First, you do not need Ant, a JDK, or a
  JDBC database to build only GSI-OpenSSH.
  Second, instead of running "make",
  run:
</para>
<screen>globus$ make gsi-openssh</screen>
<para>
  This will install the GSI-OpenSSH client and server programs.
  For client-only installations, simply do not configure or use the installed server.
</para>
</section>

</chapter>

  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    href="../Util_OpenSSH_Interface_Config_Frag.xml"/>

<chapter id="gsiopenssh-admin-deploying"><title>Deploying</title>

<orderedlist>

<listitem><para>
To install the GSI-Enabled OpenSSH Server on most systems, you must be
a privileged user, such as root.

<screen>sh$ /bin/su - root </screen>

Note: If your system functions like this and you attempt to run these
commands as a user other than root, these commands should fail.
</para>
</listitem>

<listitem><para>(optional) Start a copy of your system's currently running SSH server
on an alternate port by running, eg.

<screen>
sh# /usr/sbin/sshd -p 2000 &amp;
</screen>

You may then choose to log in to this server and continue the rest of
these steps from that shell.  We recommend doing this since some sshd
shutdown scripts do particularly nasty things like killing <emphasis>all</emphasis>
of the running SSH servers on a system, not just the parent server
that may be listening on port 22.

Roughly translated, this step is about guaranteeing that an alternate
method of access is available should the main SSH server be shutdown
and your connection via that server be terminated.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Locate your server's startup/shutdown script directory.  On some
systems this directory may be located at /etc/rc.d/init.d, but since
this location is not constant across operating systems, for the
purposes of this document we will refer to this directory as INITDIR.
Consult your operating system's documentation for your system's
location.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Run the following command.

<screen>
sh# mv $INITDIR/sshd $INITDIR/sshd.bak
</screen>
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Either copy or link the new sshd script to your system's
startup/shutdown script directory.

<screen>
sh# cp $GLOBUS_LOCATION/sbin/SXXsshd $INITDIR/sshd
</screen>
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Shutdown the currently running main SSH server.

<screen>
sh# $INITDIR/sshd.bak stop
</screen>
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Provided you still have a connection to the machine, start the new SSH
server.

<screen>
sh# $INITDIR/sshd start
</screen>
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Test the new server by connecting to the standard SSH port (22) and
authenticating via multiple methods.  Especially test that GSI
authentication works correctly.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
If you are performing a new install, or if the old server was not
configured to be started at run-time and shutdown automatically at
system halt or reboot, either use a system utility such as RedHat's
chkconfig to configure the system for the correct run-levels, or
manually link up the correct run-levels.

<screen>
sh# /sbin/chkconfig sshd reset
</screen>

The recommended run-levels are listed in a set of comments within the
SXXsshd startup script.  For example, on standard Unix systems we
recommend running the GSI-Enabled OpenSSH server in run-levels two,
three, four, and five.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Finally, if, as a precautionary measure, you started a SSH server on
an alternate port in order to complete the install process, you can
now safely stop all instances of that server.
</para></listitem>

</orderedlist>

</chapter>

<chapter id="gsiopenssh-admin-testing"><title>Testing</title>

<orderedlist>
<listitem><para>
Edit the file $GLOBUS_LOCATION/sbin/SXXsshd so that the GSI-Enabled
OpenSSH server starts up on an alternate port.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Run the command
<screen>
sh# $GLOBUS_LOCATION/sbin/SXXsshd start
</screen>
and verify that the server is running by checking that it both shows
up in a process listing and creates a file named
$GLOBUS_LOCATION/var/sshd.pid.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
From a remote machine attempt to connect to the local server on the
modified test port using the standard SSH authentication methods plus
authenticating via your GSI credentials.
This may require you to authorize these users via an appropriate entry
in the grid-mapfile.
</para></listitem>

<listitem><para>
Stop the SSH server by running the command
<screen>
sh# $GLOBUS_LOCATION/sbin/SXXsshd stop
</screen>
and reverse any changes you made that altered the port on which the server resided upon startup.  After this step,
running SXXsshd start should start the server on the default port (22).
</para></listitem>
</orderedlist>
</chapter>

  <chapter id="gsiopenssh-admin-security_considerations"><title>Security Considerations </title>
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    href="../Util_OpenSSH_Security_Considerations_Frag.xml"/>
</chapter>
  
  <chapter id="gsiopenssh-admin-debugging">
  <title>Debugging</title>
    <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    href="../Util_OpenSSH_Logging_Frag.xml"/>
</chapter>
  
  
  <chapter id="gsiopenssh-admin-troubleshooting"><title>Troubleshooting</title>
  <para>Please see the <ulink url="http://grid.ncsa.illinois.edu/ssh/ts_common.html">GSI-OpenSSH Troubleshooting Page</ulink>.</para>
</chapter>
  
  <xi:include href="../Util_OpenSSH_Usage_Statistics_Frag.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"/>
  
</book>
